Finding Aid for William L. Clements Library records, 1923-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William L. Clements Library records
1923-1964
William L. Clements Library.
87346 Bimu C440 2
Records, 1923-1964, of the William L. Clements Library of the University of Michigan; contain official correspondence and other materials.
31 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the Clements Library (donor no. 1333 ).
The record group is open without restriction.
William Clements was a Bay City businessman who served as regent from 1910 to 1933. An Early interest in collecting books crystallized around gathering rare books related to American history that were printed before 1800. In 1921, he gave his collection of books, manuscripts and maps to the university and provided a building to house them, which was opened in 1923. Mr. Clements continued to serve on the Committee of Management of the Clements Library until his death in 1934. He worked closely with Randolph G. Adams, who served as director, in broadening the scope of the collection to cover American history from 1493 to the 1850s. The collection is particularly rich in U.S. revolutionary sources from British as well as American participants.
Directors of the Clements Library have been: Randolph G. Adams, 1923-1951; Colton Storm, acting director, 1951-1953; Howard H. Peckham, 1953-1978; and John C. Dann, 1978-current.
The records of the William L. Clements Library contain correspondence regarding the operation of the library, acquisitions by gift or purchase, and a topical file maintained by the directors. The records are organized into three series: Topical Files circa 1923-1949, Topical Files circa 1923-1964, and Correspondence. All three series contain correspondence, and overlap to a large degree with regard to years covered.
Subjects:
Archives--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; Peckham, Howard H. (Howard Henry), 1910-1995.
- Topical Files, circa 1923-1949
  - A-Mi (Box 1)
  - Mi-Sw (Box 2)
  - T-W (Box 3)
- Topical Files, circa 1923-1964
  - Am-Am (Box 4)
  - Am (Box 5)
  - Am-B (1959-1964) (Box 6)
  - B (to 1958)-Bi (1935-1946) (Box 7)
  - Bi-C (1959-1964) (Box 8)
  - C-Co (Box 9)
  - Co-De (Box 10)
  - Di-E (Box 11)
  - F (Box 12)
  - G (Box 13)
  - H-Ha (Box 14)
  - He-Je (Box 15)
  - Jo-La (Box 16)
  - La-Ls (Box 17)
  - Mac (Box 18)
  - Mad-University of Michigan (1959-1964) (Box 19)
  - University of Michigan (to 1958)-Ne (Box 20)
  - Ne-O (Box 21)
  - P (Box 22)
  - P-Q (Box 23)
  - R (Box 24)
  - R-S (Box 25)
  - S (Box 26)
  - S (Box 27)
  - S-T (Box 28)
  - U-V (Box 29)
  - V-W (Box 30)
  - W-Z (Box 31)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1953-1964 (Box 31)